Bernard J. Koch

COMPUTATIONAL SOCIAL SCIENTIST

bernard.koch@gmail.com bernardjkoch.com github.com/kochbj mlinkedin.com/in/bernardkoch

I am a computational social scientist (data scientist) focused on science and culture. In my research, I work with Bayesian hierarchical modeling, deep learning, causal inference, and qualitative interviews. Before graduate school, I worked as a Bioinformatics Fellow at NIH and as a front-end developer and science education researcher at AAAS (publisher of Science).

EXPERIENCE

UCLA, Los Angeles, CA — *PhD Student* 2016 -

- Researching how organization of scientific fields affects productivity, ethics, and public reception of science
- Wrote 40-page review on deep learning for observational causal inference with extensive tutorials in Tensorflow 2
- Developing Bayesian models for demographic rate analysis

AAAS, Washington, DC — Research Assistant 2014 - 2016

- Front-end development of online science education tools
- Developed standardized tests through focus groups, 1000+ student pilot studies, and item response theory analysis

NIH, Bethesda, MD — *Bioinformatics Fellow* 2010-2011, 2013-2014

· Worked on genome assembly/annotation projects, phylogenomics of animal kingdom, consulting

EDUCATION

UCLA — PhD in Sociology 2018 -**UCLA** — MA in Sociology 2016 - 2018 **Swarthmore College** — BA in Biology 2009 - 2013

- Machine learning: classification regression, clustering,
- Deep Learning: GNN, Transformers
- GLMs: OLS, GLM, Mixed **Effects**
- Qualitative: Interviews, Focus Groups

LANGUAGES

PROGRAMMING:

Fluent: Python, R, Bash Intermediate: Tensorflow, SQL, Javascript

 SPOKEN: English (fluent), Spanish (limited proficiency)

GRANTS & FELLOWSHIPS

I have won \$230,000+ in competitive grants from:

- NSF (GRFP, DDRIG)
- UCLA
- Russell Sage Foundation
- J. Templeton Foundation

SELECT PUBLICATIONS

- Koch BJ, Denton E, Hanna A, Foster JG. Reduced, Reused and Recycled: The Life of a ML Dataset. NeurIPS [oral], 2021.
- Jiang S, Koch BJ, Sun Y. HINTS: time series prediction via dynamic heterogeneous information network embedding. WWW [oral], 2021.
- Koch BJ, Sainburg T, Geraldo PE, Jiang S, Sun Y, Foster JG. Deep Learning of Potential Outcomes. Preprint.
- Koch BJ, Silvestro D, Foster JG. The evolutionary dynamics of cultural change (As told through the birth and brutal, blackened death of Metal music). R&R at American Journal of Sociology.
- Brand JE, Xu J, Koch BJ, Geraldo PE. Uncovering sociological effect heterogeneity using tree-based machine learning. **Sociological Methodology**, 2021.
- Ryan JF, Pang K, Schnitzler CE, Nguyen A-D, Moreland RT, Simmons DK, Koch BJ, et al., Baxevanis AD. The genome of the ctenophore Mnemiopsis leidyi. **Science**, 2013.